you know what your story has gotten all
sorts of national publicity in the U.S
and I I know you're in London and I
don't know if it's gotten a lot of
oppress there as well but it crossed my
feed and I
was like I have to talk to this guy
because it's it's almost like fake like
a movie like how is it even possible
especially with some of the details
because one of the fascinating details
is that as a child on your bedroom wall
you had written your goals and one of
them was one day I will work at Oxford
or Cambridge which everyone knows it's
like the the creme de La Creme the top
academic institutions on the planet and
as a kid who couldn't speak that seems
like a pretty outlandish goal so what do
you remember about making that goal
because you were a child
um because see that's it's so yeah thank
you so much I mean I guess it's surreal
one of the things that's kind of been
really so I guess surreal I I don't know
just it's been a lot to take in there's
you wake up one morning and
you know your contemporaries know what
you do which is very different and then
you go to bed and you wake up the next
morning and the entire world knows what
you do so you know it's
I I I've been told that over half a
billion people worldwide have viewed the
articles
which is kind of insane
um because yeah I I myself I'm not on
social media I'm quite a quiet private
person but
um it's hard to kind of comprehend there
are so many amazing powerful stories
every day and why people take interest
in this particular one but maybe that's
not for me to know
um and I mean in terms of the Oxford and
Cambridge thing that I wrote my mom and
dad's wall
um I was
um that was in
2012 2012 I did that so I was um doing
some work in my mum and Dad's bedroom
decorating and I would have been
um 27 at the time
um and was about to I so in the previous
life I was a phys ed teacher
um and kind of was embarking on my
journey in higher education and started
my I just started my PhD and wrote three
things which would be you know
um the three famous things now I wanted
to look after my friends make sure that
my um mum and dad were well
um and my final ambition was the one
they worked at Oxford Cambridge
admittedly
I didn't know what capacity that would
be in and it's easy to sit here and say
I truly believed in that goal
um I don't want to sit here and say that
but what I would say is that um I worked
as hard as I could and I thought if I
can get within touching distance of it
then maybe I'll be presented with an
opportunity one day and I would hope
that all the experiences and all the
things that I've learned upon that
Journey if the opportunity should
present itself but I'll be well equipped
enough to hopefully at least compete so
my big thing in life is being able to
compete
that doesn't necessarily mean you win it
just means I want to compete I want to
be able to be competitive and whoever
gets it give them a really good fight
you know and um
and and unfortunately I I got the um I
got the W on this one but um but I feel
very very fortunate
of your humility and how you talk about
it and it is a weird thing because many
people who get the kind of Spotlight
like you're getting don't expect it you
know people that go into acting or you
know again where you live if you're the
monarchy these people know their whole
life that their the goal is to be a
really big deal and that was not your
goal and suddenly you wake up and half a
billion people or I mean it's like a
ridiculous number
um especially when you had your
diagnosis when you were a child and so
when I think about you you have this
humility and uh this desire to work hard
and you had this diagnosis that would
have made those goals seem
frankly ridiculous right for for many
years
that tells me that there were people
around you who are encouraging you and
there were people around you who said
you you can do it you should try the
next thing and they didn't accept
perhaps what the Physicians are what the
experts told them
is that and that's true for your life
right your your mother was
was encouraging yeah Christy um my mom
was a stalled and on top of that like
very determined that um
you know she she vehemently rejected the
medical model of disability and really
embraced the facial model of disability
and I think a lot of her thinking was
really positioned around
you know
um
the capacity for individuals to do great
things is not confined to a a rigorous a
rigid hypothesis on what human beings
can be and what can become and her whole
thing was like if I expand his way of
thinking through the use of music
through the use of sport through the use
of understanding social interaction
because that's a very difficult thing
for a lot of artists to experience that
kind of social interaction but if I can
equip him with these skills hopefully
he'll help him as he gets older and
maybe we can bit by bit break some of
the kind of
um psychological
diagnosis in terms of those really
strict confined boundaries that
boundaries that individuals have set for
um for myself and
I mean I don't want to say the rest is
history but I I guess the rest is
history
um I
I was very very fortunate to have the
parents I did even more fortunate to
have the mother I did
um who
who basically
um as many neurodivergent parents do and
they didn't give up on me and my mum
didn't give up on me and if I've
achieved
anything of any note in my life it's
really down to my mother and then my
shooter that I met at College
um Sandra Sandry who basically instilled
this mentality in me
um in terms of the abandonment of fear
and what fear does in terms of fear
fears of paralyzer is a disabler it's
it's
it kind of renders us still and
when that was exercised out of me in
some respects
um you know Sandra's whole thing was
we're going to try and take on the world
and win and um
if if I never met him I don't think I'd
be I'd be sat here speaking to your good
self right now Christy
I'm gonna try and take on the world and
win and to do that means you have to
Define it right so I think that's one of
the other things about your story that's
so compelling which perhaps is why it's
reaching all
regions of the world is because you put
a goal out there and then you had people
around you who said yes let's try for
that
it's remarkable because many people who
are high functioning not diagnosed with
autism not diagnosed with some of the
things that you're diagnosed with don't
have that they don't have people around
them saying let's set some goals and
then I'm going to help you get the
mindset so we can get a w
yeah and that's the thing Christine I
think the one thing I would say
um and I can be quite self-deprecating
but this is this is true you know
sometimes I think the most important
thing you can know is yourself and be
honest with yourself I I don't have any
remarkable academic ability
um and the academic ability is what
Sandra always referred to me as skill
but what I did have was Will and he said
what we need to do is drag skill into a
dogfight with Will that's what we need
to do we need to drag skill into this
dogfight of Will and it needs to always
be will versus skill
and his whole thing was
um hard work beat Talent when talent
doesn't work hard so you can be as
talented as you like but if you actually
don't have the ability to work hard the
person who doesn't have as much talent
but is willing to you know is that kind
of famous Al Pacino speech in any given
something where he says like you know
are you willing to die for that inch and
it's the man who's willing to order
person who's willing to die for that
inch that will make up those those
inches um and I think
I think if I had to sum myself up it I
was willing to do anything I was willing
I sacrificed 16 years of my life working
punching above my weight you know
sleeping two three hours a night
um giving it everything I've got knowing
that I wasn't good enough to give
anything less
you know and I always say
um Christie if I'd given one millisecond
of effort less than I did I really don't
think I'd be here I think it required
every single
thing within me to kind of manifest that
and to work as hard as I can knowing
that I just I didn't have the talent so
you know you know you get situations
where
you know if you're a boxer you know you
want to be able to go into a ring and
get somebody out of there with you know
you've got to have it you wanna have a
kind of a killer a one-hitter quitter
you can get someone out there in two or
three rounds but you know I'm a 12 round
fighter and not that I want to be but it
means that you know I guess the point
people don't people see the end point
but I don't see the bit in between and
I'm punch drunk you know I've taken a
lot of shots to the Head
um and I wouldn't recommend people to
necessarily do that but it's also a
testament to
um
the indomitable Spirit of human beings
just how much like you know I guess in
some ways as Rocky says how much you can
take and keep winning like and it's not
and that's how winning is done and I I
don't think life is defined purely to
winning because I actually think the
greatest lessons you learn are when you
lose and if you can lose with Grace
you'll be a very good winner
um and you know in my life I've lost
more than I've won but because I was
such a good loser it meant that when my
time came to win I knew how to win with
Grace and that's quite an important
thing
um particularly as I think a lot of
people don't necessarily know how to do
that so my first thing when I win is I
think about how my opponent or how the
other person may feel haven't been on
the other side so many times and the
first thing you want to be able to do is
to congratulate that individual on their
efforts and recognize we've all been
there and to tell them to keep going you
know so um
and there's an empathy there that's not
disposable I genuinely mean that when I
say that and I guess I've just um
I don't know Christy when when people
say like I want something really badly
you know
I remember Sandra asking me you say you
want it badly but how badly do you want
it what are you willing to do within the
bounds of morals and ethics to achieve
your goal
and I was willing I was willing to give
up everything
and give it everything I had and
by the grace of God
um yeah I'm sat here now and I've been
very very fortunate but I also think
that um it always comes back to the same
thing it's about style and I don't mean
style in terms of how people dress
um or sartorially I mean style in terms
of
how you carry yourself how you treated
people did you bring people along did
you pull the ladder up were you kind to
everyone you meet you met were you you
know did you make people feel seen did
you make people feel heard did you
create space for people did you with
with anything that came good to you did
you kind of break bread with many people
did you share what you had it's all of
those things and as my dad kind of
reiterated to me all the time on this
journey you can't be buried with your
books so it really does come down to how
you treated people and that's what I
mean about the style like I think it's
not so much getting there for me it's
the way I've done it and I think the way
I've done it is probably the thing that
people are beginning to learn more about
now which is maybe why people
feel some sort of affinity because of
the way I've done it and and obviously
that means a hell of a lot because it
was always about the style you know and
when I say style I don't like I said I
don't mean it sartorially even though
I'm tailoring is like my passion but I'm
talking about style in terms of how you
do it you know and it's it's always
about you know as as Maya Angelou once
famously said it's about how you made
people feel and I think
um battle was always the most important
thing for me you know um not through
this particular act or achievement in
inverted commas but just generally
speaking could people speak of you 15 20
years ago and say
you know Christy was a really cool
person you know she's really really cool
and you know what she hasn't actually
really changed she's still the same cool
person I knew 20 years ago but that's
the kind of thing that you know
that those are the kind of things that
matter and it's not something that
people necessarily have to say to you
but it's enough for people to think that
you're the same person and and actually
you haven't just started being nice
because you're you've got people
watching you you've always been like
that and those those are the things that
matter
[Music]
thank you